Guide to the Wesley Works archive, 1676-1996 and undated, bulk 1724-1791, 1960-1996 RL.01368
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Sermons Series (Volumes 1-4), 1725-1798, 1844, 1968-1988 and undated, 27 boxes
  - Texts Subseries, 1771 and undated
    The texts date from the same general period as the Stemmata Subseries above, and much of the editorial work would have been done in the late-1970s to mid-1980s. See Collection Overview for discussion of the difference between "preliminary texts" and "styled preliminary texts." Arranged chronologically.
    - Preliminary texts, Sermons 1-37, undated, 7 folders (Box 6)
    - Preliminary texts, Sermons 38-77, undated, 7 folders (Box 7)
    - Preliminary texts, Sermons 78-108, undated, 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Preliminary texts, nine sermons added 1771, undated: 13-15, 20, 39, 43, 51-53, 129, undated, Folders 1-2 of 3 (Box 8)
    - Preliminary texts, nine sermons added 1771, undated: 13-15, 20, 39, 43, 51-53, 129, undated, Folder 3 of 3 (Box 9)
    - Styled preliminary texts, Sermons 1-36, undated, 6 folders (Box 9)
    - Styled preliminary texts, Sermons 37-80, undated, 7 folders (Box 10)
    - Styled preliminary texts, Sermons 81-113, undated, 5 folders (Box 11)
    - Styled preliminary texts, Sermons 114, 127-128, 130-143, undated, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Styled preliminary texts, various sermons, alternate numbering, undated, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - Sermons I Subseries, 1977-1984 and undated
    Correspondence, notes, typescripts, and proofs for Sermons I, 1-33, Volume 1 (1984) of The Works of John Wesley. This was the first volume published by Abingdon Press, following Oxford University Press's withdrawal from the project. Arranged as received, roughly in order of the process of composition and editing. Proofs and galleys are slightly oversize materials.
    - Correspondence and copy editing questions, 1977-1983 and undated, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Preface and prelims, 1979 (Box 12)
    - Preface proofreading, 1983 (Box 12)
    - Typescripts, full set: introduction, preface, and sermons, copy edited and corrected, undated, 12 folders (Box 12-13)
    - Vol. 1 revisions, 1983 (Box 13)
    - Proof design--notes and correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 13)
    - Notes on Vol. 1 proofs, 1978-1984, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Final markups on prints, 1984 (Box 14)
    - Proofs and galleys, 1983-1984, 25 oversize folders (Box 21-24)
      Multiple stages of editing represented; includes Baker's edits of Oxford University Press galleys. Arranged as received, generally in production order.
  - Sermons II Subseries, 1983-1989 and undated
    Correspondence, notes, typescripts, and proofs for Sermons II, 34-70, Volume 2 (1985) of The Works of John Wesley. Arranged as received.
    - Copy editing, 1983 (Box 14)
    - Typescripts, sermons 34-70--full set, copy edited and corrected, 1984, 5 folders (Box 14)
    - Typescripts, notes to sermons 34-70--full set, copy edited and corrected, 1984, Folder 1 of 5 (Box 14)
    - Typescripts, notes--full set, copy edited and corrected, 1984, Folders 2-5 of 5 (Box 15)
    - Proofs correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 15)
    - Galley notes, 1989 (Box 15)
    - Galleys, 1985, 6 folders (Box 25)
  - Sermons III Subseries, 1985-1987 and undated
    Correspondence, notes, typescripts, and proofs for Sermons III, 71-114, Volume 3 (1986) of The Works of John Wesley. Arranged as received. Galleys are slightly oversize materials.
    - Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1985-1987 (Box 15)
    - Typescripts, sermons 71-114--full set, copy edited and corrected, circa 1986, Folders 1-3 of 4 (Box 15)
    - Typescripts, sermons 71-114--full set, copy edited and corrected, circa 1986, Folder 4 of 4 (Box 16)
    - Typescripts, notes to sermons 71-114--full set, copy edited and corrected, circa 1986, 4 folders (Box 16)
    - Notes on proofs, undated (Box 16)
    - Galleys, 1985, 6 folders (Box 26)
    - Galleys, 1985-1986, 5 folders (Box 27)
  - Sermons IV Subseries, 1725-1741, 1772, 1844, 1968-1987 and undated
    Correspondence, notes, typescripts, and proofs for Sermons IV, 115-151, Volume 4 (1987) of The Works of John Wesley. The 18th century dates used for this subseries reflects the presence of numerous photocopied materials filed with this volume. Arranged as received.
    - Research--general, 1844, 1972, 1983 and undated (Box 17)
    - Research, Sermons 133-151, 1725-1741, 1772, 1968-1972 and undated, 17 folders (Box 17)
      Mainly photocopies and transcriptions of sermons from various manuscript originals.
    - Typescripts: Sermons 115-151, undated, 3 folders (Box 17)
    - Typescripts: Appendices A-D, 1982, 1987 and undated, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Typescripts: Bibliographical Lists and Charts, 1983 and undated, 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Typescripts, copy edited: Preface-Sermon 151, 1987, 4 folders (Box 18)
    - Typescripts, copy edited: Notes, 1987, 4 folders (Box 19)
    - Typescripts, copy edited: Appendices, indices, and errata, 1986-1987 and undated, Folders 1-5 of 7 (Box 19)
    - Typescripts, copy edited: Appendices, indices, and errata, 1986-1987 and undated, Folders 6-7 of 7 (Box 20)
    - Page proof correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 20)
    - Proofs, 1987, 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Galleys, with Baker's edits, 1987, 4 folders (Box 27)
- Explanatory Notes upon the New Testament Series (Volumes 5-6), 1676, 1755-1759, 1974-1988 and undated, 5 boxes
  The series, Explanatory Notes upon the New Testament, houses correspondence, research, and typescripts for Volumes 5 and 6. Most of the material here documents the efforts of Baker and the original unit editor, John Lawson, to arrive at a full working draft of John Wesley's commentary on the New Testament. There is also material concerning The Remains or Several Select Scriptures Of the New Testament opened and explained of Robert Gell, D. D. (1676), an Arminian commentary on the New Testament. An extensive, perhaps full, photocopy of this edition of "Gell's Remains" is included here, along with notes by Baker in which he traces Gell's influence on Wesley.
  Correspondence, research, and typescripts for Volumes 5 and 6. Most of the material here documents the editors' efforts to arrive at a preliminary text, thus photocopies and typescripts of various editions of Wesley's work comprise the bulk of this series. Files are arranged in the categories of correspondence, research, and texts, with the last category further arranged in order of composition (stemmata, preliminary texts, and styled texts). Baker's main correspondent here is original unit editor John Lawson (d. 2003); the other unit editor was Scott Jones.
  - Correspondence, 1974 (Box 28)
  - Research: Gell's Remains, 1676-1759, 1988 (Box 28)
    Proofs, introductory note, and photocopies of original material, 1676-1759.
  - Research: Lawson's Marked Copies, undated, 5 folders (Box 28)
    Scope: Matthew-Acts. Pages of an unspecified edition of Explanatory Notes cut out and taped to typing paper, to which Lawson added notes in the margins.
  - Research: Appendices A-B - photocopies with notes, undated, 2 folders (Box 28)
  - Research: Xerox of stemma, undated (Box 28)
  - Preliminary Texts, undated, Folders 1-7 of 13 (Box 29)
  - Preliminary Texts, undated, Folders 8-13 of 13 (Box 30)
  - Styled Preliminary Texts, undated, Folders 1-2 of 18 (Box 30)
  - Styled Preliminary Texts, undated, Folders 3-10 of 18 (Box 31)
  - Styled Preliminary Texts, undated, Folders 11-18 of 18 (Box 32)
  - Notes on New Testament Materials, 21 folders (Box 113)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes research files, sources, proofs, and marked photocopy typescripts of drafts of Explanatory Notes on the New Testament.
  - Notes on New Testament Materials, 14 folders (Box 114)
    Typescript drafts of notes arranged by books of the New Testament. Books included: Mark, Luke, John, Acts, Romans, Hebrews, 1st and 2nd Corinthians, Timothy, Galatians, and Matthew.
- A Collection of Hymns for the Use of the People called Methodists Series (Volume 7), 1965-1983 and undated, 6 boxes
  One of the earlier volumes published, in 1983, is represented in the series A Collection of Hymns for the Use of the People called Methodists. This volume focused on printing a critical text of John Wesley's most famous and popular collection of hymns, which first appeared in 1780 and has gone through many editions since then. Discussion, planning, and research for Volume 7 began in the mid-1960s and is documented by a large volume of correspondence between Baker and the two unit editors, Franz Hildebrandt and Oliver Beckerlegge.
  Files for Volume 7 contain correspondence between Frank Baker, Franz Hildebrandt, Oliver A. Beckerlegge, and James Dale; typescripts of the introduction by Hildebrandt; the project of James Dale in discovering literary allusions in the hymnody corpus; the final typescripts, galleys, and page proofs of the volume. Volume 7 was first published in 1983, by Oxford University Press, and republished in 1989 under the Abingdon imprint; the unit editors were Franz Hildebrandt and Oliver Beckerlegge, assisted by James Dale. Arranged in categories as received.
  - Correspondence, 1965-1983 (Box 33)
    - Early correspondence, 1965-1976, 2 folders (Box 33)
    - General Planning, 1970-1980 (Box 33)
    - Hildebrandt, 1974-1978 (Box 33)
    - Chronological, 1978-1983, Folders 1-5 of 6 (Box 33)
    - Chronological, 1978-1983, Folder 6 of 6 (Box 34)
  - Introduction--drafts and sections, 1970-1979 and undated (Box 34)
    - Franz Hildebrandt draft under revision, 1974 Mar. (Box 34)
    - Last draft, undated (Box 34)
    - Dale, James, 1970-1979, 3 folders (Box 34)
      Correspondence, drafts, and notes on literary allusions for Dale's section of the introduction, "The Literary Setting of Wesley's Hymns."
  - Research and other files, 1976, 1984 and undated (Box 34)
    - Hymmbook type samples, 1976 (Box 34)
    - Identifying Scripture--John Lawson, undated (Box 34)
    - Proposal for Concordance to 1780 Hymn Book, 1984 and undated (Box 34)
    - Scriptural allusions, undated, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 34)
    - Scriptural allusions, undated, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 35)
    - Verse lists--indexes, undated (Box 35)
  - Typescripts, 1979 and undated
    - Styled typescript, undated, 10 folders (Box 35)
    - Variants marked, undated, Folder 1 of 4 (Box 35)
    - Variants marked, undated, Folders 2-4 of 4 (Box 36)
    - Typescript, 1979 and undated, Folders 1-4 of 7 (Box 36)
    - Typescript, 1979 and undated, Folders 5-7 of 7 (Box 37)
    - Typescript of appendices, undated, 2 folders (Box 37)
  - Galleys and Proofs, 1981-1982
    - Galleys A, 1981, 5 folders (Box 38)
    - Galleys B, 1981, 5 folders (Box 38)
    - Page Proofs, 1982 (Box 38)
- Worship Series (Volume 8), 1737-1792, 1883, 1922, 1964-1992 and undated, 4 boxes
  The Worship Series holds materials for Volume 8, a collection of John Wesley's printed liturgical works. The materials here reflect early stages in the editorial process, consisting mainly of extensive photocopies and typescripts that were compiled in the late 1970s and early 1980s in order to derive stemma and establish authoritative texts. Despite the early date of these materials in the history of the project, they include a full preliminary typescript of Volume 8, edited by Baker. Another highlight here is some later, related work Frank Baker did on Hymns on the Lord's Supper, resulting in a 1995 address to a meeting of the Charles Wesley Society.
  Material is arranged as received, gathered under the title of each individual work to be reprinted in the Worship volume. This titles are then arranged in the order reflected in early drafts of the planned table of contents. Volume 8 has not been published. The unit editor at the time these materials were produced was Raymond George, with whom Baker corresponds here; since then, Geoffrey Wainwright and Karen Westerfield Tucker were also added as unit editors.
  - Correspondence, 1978-1986 (Box 39)
  - A Collection of Forms of Prayer for Every Day in the Week--photocopies and typescript, 1737-1772, 1965-1978 and undated, 7 folders (Box 39)
  - A Collection of Prayers for Families--photocopies, stemma, and typescripts 1743-1786, 1978 and undated, 3 folders (Box 39)
  - Prayers for Children--photocopies and typescript, 1772-1777 and undated (Box 39)
  - Directions for Renewing our Covenant with God--correspondence and typescript, 1978 and undated (Box 39)
  - The Sunday Service of the Methodists: Correspondence, notes, photocopies, and typescripts, 1784-1792, 1969-1992 and undated, 3 folders (Box 39)
  - The Sunday Service of the Methodists: Notes on JW letter of 1784 Sept. 10, 1964-1970 (Box 40)
  - The Sunday Service of the Methodists: 2nd edition, printout from microfilm, 1786, 1883, and 1922, 3 folders (Box 40)
  - The Sunday Service of the Methodists: full edited typescript, with notes on stemma, 1978, 4 folders (Box 40)
  - The Sunday Service and the Book of Common Prayer, 1784-1785, 1984 (Box 40)
  - The Christian Sacrament and Sacrifice--photocopies of editions, 1754, 1790 and undated (Box 40)
  - Hymns on the Lord's Supper, 1745-1786 and undated, 9 folders (Box 40-41)
    Photocopies of editions 1-9, typescripts, bibliographic research, correspondence, and drafts for an address by FB to Charles Wesley Society, 1995 Oct. 14.
  - Volume 8--typescripts, undated, 9 folders (Box 41-42)
- The Methodist Societies Series (Volumes 9-10), 1739-1799, 1864-1869, 1958-1991 and undated, 12 boxes
  The Methodist Societies unit is divided into two volumes and subseries: History, Nature, and Design (Vol. 9); and Minutes of the Conference (Vol. 10). Completed in 1989, History, Nature, and Design collects a variety of documents, published intermittently throughout Wesley's life, in which in which he attempted to define what a Methodist and Methodism were, and how its societies were to be organized within the Church of England. The materials gathered here contain research, typescripts, and proofs that outline the entire history of the volume's inception, development, and publication. Minutes of the Conference, on the other hand, did not appear until 2011, some twenty to thirty years after these materials were researched and written, so this subseries reflects only the early stages of the volume's development. The subseries consists mainly of photocopies, although many have been densely annotated by Baker, collated, and transcribed into preliminary typescripts. The highlight of this subseries may lie in Baker's unpublished index of John Wesley's preachers. Deemed too long for the published volume, this work compiles brief but detailed chronologies of some 600 18th-century Methodist preachers in England: where they served, when they moved, and other highlights of their lives and careers.
  Arranged in two subseries that comprise volumes 9 and 10, respectively: History, Nature, and Design; and Minutes of the Conference. See subseries notes for further detail.
  - History, Nature, and Design Subseries, 1742-1793, 1970-1989 and undated
    Correspondence, notes, typescripts, and proofs for History, Nature, and Design, Volume 9 (1989) of The Works of John Wesley. The primary correspondents here are Baker and unit editor Rupert E. Davies, although J. Hamby Barton, at one time co-editor with Davies, appears often in the 1970s files. Arranged as received, in these categories: correspondence; drafts of Davies' Introduction; texts of the individual Wesley works collected in this volume; preliminary texts and Baker's stemmata for all the constituent letters; and concluding with galleys of the final stages of publication.
    - Correspondence--Rupert Davies, J. Hamby Barton, Dick Heitzenrater, and others, 1970-1989, 2 folders (Box 43)
    - Introduction--correspondence, drafts, and comments, 1983-1987 and undated, 3 folders (Box 43)
    - Introductory notes to chapters--draft, undated (Box 43)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: The Character of a Methodist--collated and styled texts, stemma, eds. A-S, 1742-1791 and undated, 2 folders (Box 43)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: The Principles of a Methodist--collated and styled texts, stemma, eds. A, C-G, 1742-1789 and undated (Box 43)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: The Nature, Design, and General Rules of the United Societies--styled texts, stemma, eds. A-2N, 1743-1793, 1988, and undated, 3 folders (Box 44)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: Rules of the Band Societies--stemma, notes, eds. A-S, 1744-1791, 1983 and undated, 2 folders (Box 44)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: Answer to the Rev. Mr. Church's Remarks--styled text, eds. A-C, [1745], 2 folders (Box 44)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: Advice to the People Called Methodists--collated and styled texts, stemma, eds. A-I, 1745-1787 and undated (Box 44)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: Modern Christianity Exemplified at Wednesbury--collated text, eds. A-D, 1745-1790 and undated (Box 44)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: The Principles of a Methodist Further Explained--styled text, stemma, eds. A-B, 1746-1771 and undated, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 44)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: The Principles of a Methodist Further Explained--styled text, stemma, eds. A-B, 1746-1771 and undated, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 45)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: Gair i'r Methodist--A Word to a Methodist--notes, eds. A-B, 1748-1751 and 1979 (Box 45)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: A Letter to a Clergyman--preliminary text, eds. A-E, 1748-1772, 1989 and undated (Box 45)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: A Plain Account of the People Called Methodists--collated text, stemma, eds. A-C, E-I, 1749-1786 and undated (Box 45)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: A Short Address to the Inhabitants of Ireland--collated text, stemma, eds. A-D, 1749-1750 and undated (Box 45)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: A Letter to the Rev. Mr. Baily of Cork--text, eds. A-C, 1750-1773 and undated (Box 45)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: A Letter to the Rev. Dr. Free--text, eds. A, D, 1758, 1773; and A Second Letter to the Rev. Dr. Free--text, ed. A, 1758 (Box 45)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: Reasons Against a Separation from the Church of England--collated text, stemma, eds. A, C-G, 1758-1788 and undated (Box 45)
    - A Letter to the Rev. Mr. Downes--preliminary text, eds. A-B, 1755, 1773 and undated (Box 45)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: A Short History of Methodism--eds. A-E, 1765-1789 and undated (Box 45)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: A Letter to the Rev. Dr. Rutherforth--eds. A-B, 1768-1773 and undated (Box 45)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: A Letter to the Rev. Mr. Fleury--preliminary text, ed. A, 1771, 1979 and undated (Box 45)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: An Answer to Mr. Rowland Hill's Tract, entitled "Imposture Detected"--eds. A-D, 1777 and undated (Box 45)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: A Letter to the Rev. Mr. Thomas Maxfield--ed. A, 1978 and undated (Box 45)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: A Short History of the People Called Methodists, undated (Box 46)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: The Case of Birstall House, undated (Box 46)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: A Letter to the Rev. Mr. Toogood, of Exeter, undated (Box 46)
    - Stemmata for Volume 9, prelim. chapter: Answer to a Letter--Bath Journal, undated (Box 46)
    - Substitute pages in editing process, 1984-1989 (Box 46)
    - Appendix of London Foundery Membership, 1985 (Box 46)
    - Working typescript, undated, 6 folders (Box 46)
    - Printer's typescript, undated, 5 folders (Box 47)
    - Page proof correspondence, 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 47)
    - Galleys (oversize), 1988, 3 folders (Box 54)
  - Minutes of the Conference Subseries (Volume 10), 1739-1799, 1864-1869, 1958-1991 and undated
    Correspondence, notes, typescripts, and proofs for Minutes of the Conference, Volume 10 (2011) of The Works of John Wesley. As with materials for volumes published during his lifetime, these are roughly arranged in a sequence that follows the editorial process, in the following categories: Correspondence, Photocopies, Preliminary Texts, and Typescripts, and Other Research Materials. The final two boxes of the subseries are devoted mainly to Baker's extensive unpublished biographical index of some 600 of JW's preachers. Unit editor for Volume 10 is Henry Rack, who took over from his predecessor, John Bowmer, in the 1980s.
    - Correspondence, 1749-1787, 1958, 1970-1990 and undated, 2 folders
      Correspondence between Baker and original Volume 10 editor John Bowmer, mainly 1970s; and between Baker and Henry Rack, Bowmer's successor, beginning mid-1980s. Also includes numerous photocopies.
      - Correspondence folders (Box 48)
    - Photocopies, 1740-1791, 1869, 1984 and undated
      Copies of various portions of the Minutes volume, many annotated by Baker.
      - Large Minutes, 1753-1789 and undated, 3 folders (Box 48)
      - Large Minutes in six successive editions, undated (Box 48)
      - Conference Journal photocopies, 1784-1791, 4 folders (Box 48)
      - Full Connexion, 1744, 1869, 1984 (Box 48)
      - Annual, 1765-1790, Folders 1-2 of 5 (Box 48)
      - Annual, 1765-1790, Folders 3-5 of 5 (Box 49)
      - Deed of Declaration, 1784-1785 (Box 49)
    - Preliminary texts and photocopies, 1744-1794, 1864, 1979-1991 and undated (Box 49)
      Predominantly edited transcriptions and preliminary texts, although also containing many photocopies.
      - Manuscript minutes, 1744-1749, 1751-1755, 1758, 1782-1791, 1979-1987 and undated, Folders 1-13 of 20 (Box 49)
        Photocopies and transcriptions of annual minutes manuscripts, as differed from printed minutes above.
      - Manuscript minutes, 1744-1749, 1751-1755, 1758, 1782-1791, 1979-1987 and undated, Folders 14-20 of 20 (Box 50)
      - Doctrinal Minutes, 1749, 1772 (Box 50)
      - American Minutes, 1773-1794, 1977-1991 and undated, 2 folders (Box 50)
        Correspondence, notes, photocopies, and typescript of FB article, Wesley and America.
      - Irish Minutes--correspondence, notes, photocopies, typescripts, 1752-1791, 1864, 1964-1986 and undated, 2 folders (Box 50)
      - Disciplinary Minutes, 1749 and undated (Box 51)
      - The Conferences, photocopies and typescripts, 1750-1764 (Box 51)
    - Typescripts, 1744-1791, 1987-1990 and undated (Box 51)
      - "Annual Minutes, 1765-1780"--edited partial typescript, undated, 3 folders (Box 51)
      - "Annual Minutes, 1765-1791"--undated, 4 folders (Box 51)
        Clean copy, incorporating changes from above and extending.
      - "Methodist Conferences in Ireland, 1765-1791"--continuing from "Annual" above, undated (Box 52)
      - "Methodist Conferences in America, 1773-1794"--continuing from "Ireland" above, undated (Box 52)
      - "Doctrinal and Disciplinary Minutes, 1749"--continuing from "America" above, undated (Box 52)
      - Early Conferences Manuscript Minutes, 1744-1764 (Box 52)
      - Large Minutes, 1753-1789, 1987-1990 and undated, Folders 1-9 of 11 (Box 52)
        Various drafts of typescripts of Large Minutes A/B, C/D, and E/F; extensive handwritten notes and edits by Baker; early index by Heizenrater.
      - Large Minutes, 1753-1789, 1987-1990 and undated, Folders 10-11 of 11 (Box 53)
      - The Early Conference: Parts I, II, III, IV, and Appendices A and B, 8 folders (Box 115)
      - The Early Conferences: Manuscript Minutes, edited, 2 folders (Box 115)
    - Other research materials, 1739-1799, 1975-1980 and undated